<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Makers on Translusion</title>
    <link>https://blog.translusion.com/maker/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Makers on Translusion</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>© Erik Engheim 2016. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    
	<atom:link href="https://blog.translusion.com/maker/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Prototyping</title>
      <link>https://blog.translusion.com/maker/prototyping/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.translusion.com/maker/prototyping/</guid>
      <description>Lets say you want to test out an idea for a robot car, DVD changing robot arm, automatic card sorter or something similar. Machining your own parts would be time consuming. So what are the options for rapid prototyping?
Lego Mindstorm The best known option and a huge community
Easy to find help and wide variety of parts. You can get hold of lego mindstorm in almost any toystore. The downside is that lego is its own world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools</title>
      <link>https://blog.translusion.com/maker/tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.translusion.com/maker/tools/</guid>
      <description>Most of these tools you can get at stores such as:
 Clas Ohlson Jernia Byggmaker Maxbo  Clas Ohlson might be your first choice because they have a good selection and are usually easily accessible in shopping centers around Norway.
Drilling holes When you drill a hole there are a lot of issues and challenges to consider:
 Is the hole straight? Do you want to put screws into it or rod or axel later?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supplies</title>
      <link>https://blog.translusion.com/maker/supplies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.translusion.com/maker/supplies/</guid>
      <description>Materials are sheets, tubes, bars, extrusions etc made of plastic, metal, wood or rubber.
Where to buy materials Bigger pieces are usually bought at hardware or home improvement stores. Smaller sized materials are can often be gotten in hobby stores catering to model builders or RC cars or airplanes.
Byggmakker Byggmakker is a usefull place to get tools, screws, nuts, bolts and wood. Apart from that not much interesting for makers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mechanical Parts</title>
      <link>https://blog.translusion.com/maker/mechanical/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.translusion.com/maker/mechanical/</guid>
      <description>I am not aiming to give an exhaustive guide here. This is mainly to get you started. I will link to more in depth articles. The problem I am trying to address here is that when you start out you end up on a wild goose chase with google to find out stuff. I will focus on mentioning mistakes I&amp;rsquo;ve made which might aid in getting the right parts or using them correctly.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>