<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Entertainment on Translusion</title>
    <link>http://translusion.github.com/categories/entertainment/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Entertainment on Translusion</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>© Erik Engheim 2016. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://translusion.github.com/categories/entertainment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Starve Together Noob Advice</title>
      <link>http://translusion.github.com/posts/dont-starve-together-donts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://translusion.github.com/posts/dont-starve-together-donts/</guid>
      <description>I have been writing about Don&amp;rsquo;t Starve before, but after watching a number of videos of Mubo Jumbo (known for MineCraft videos) and Grian play Don&amp;rsquo;t Starve Together I realize there are a lot of things even fairly experienced players have noe clue about, which makes their game significantly harder than it needs to be.
So in this post I would like to go through some of the mistakes Mubo Jumbo and Grian make while playing Don&amp;rsquo;t Starve Together, while giving them some advice on how to improve their game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Starve Evolved Strategy</title>
      <link>http://translusion.github.com/posts/dont-starve-strategy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://translusion.github.com/posts/dont-starve-strategy/</guid>
      <description>Almost a year ago I wrote about playing Don’t Starve. I’ve had long breaks from it but had a burst playing it again a lot lately.
So I wanted to write an updated strategy guide now that I feel I am a much better Don’t Starve Player. Surviving any number of days in Don’t Starve doesn’t seem that difficult anymore. Don’t Starve Reign of Giants is a bit trickier to not screw up though.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t Starve for PS4</title>
      <link>http://translusion.github.com/posts/dont-starve-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://translusion.github.com/posts/dont-starve-review/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t play much computer games anymore. Family and small kids limits time, but equally important I simply don&amp;rsquo;t find them as fun anymore as I once did. Not long ago I got a Playstation 4 and I was eager to look at the beautiful graphics which could now be rendered. I got a bunch of third or first person shooters which all looked beautiful and amazing. But eventually they all ended up boring me.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>