<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Economics on Translusion</title>
    <link>http://blog.translusion.com/categories/economics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Economics on Translusion</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>© Erik Engheim 2016. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://blog.translusion.com/categories/economics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Indispensable and Other Myths</title>
      <link>http://blog.translusion.com/posts/ceo-salaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.translusion.com/posts/ceo-salaries/</guid>
      <description>A lot of people assume that CEO salaries are completely determined by the market. But saying that something is determined by the market isn&amp;rsquo;t very informative. The market as described in Economic text books full or rational individuals with perfect information about the products they are buying rarely exists.
Michael B. Dorff shows in his book &amp;ldquo;Indispensable and Other Myths&amp;rdquo; how the &amp;ldquo;market&amp;rdquo; for CEOs isn&amp;rsquo;t really a market. The most refreshing thing about the book I think is that he shows how essentially both sides of the debate about CEO salaries are quite wrong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the US can&#39;t teach the world</title>
      <link>http://blog.translusion.com/posts/america-cant-teach-the-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.translusion.com/posts/america-cant-teach-the-world/</guid>
      <description>While the US isn&amp;rsquo;t the richest country in the world in per capita GDP, it is by far the richest large country. It can boast of impressive results in science and innovation. Does that mean that anyone whishing to obtain similar levels of prosperity have to follow the American model for economic system and organization of society? My short answer is &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo;.
The US is an outlier which has too many advantages not related to the organization of its economy or society.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why American states cannot be compared to European countries</title>
      <link>http://blog.translusion.com/posts/europe-is-not-america/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.translusion.com/posts/europe-is-not-america/</guid>
      <description>It is populare with peeing contests between America and Europe either in terms of GDP numbers, level of development, education, crime and what not. Of course regardless of how entertaining these sort of comparisons are, they are essentially apple to oranges comparisons. Europeans might score points by pointing to a number of of smaller European countries with very favorable statistics in a number of areas such as unemployment, human development index, crime rates, GDP etc.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>