<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics on Trans lusion</title>
    <link>http://translusion.github.com/categories/politics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Politics on Trans lusion</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://translusion.github.com/categories/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The significance of intention in war</title>
      <link>http://translusion.github.com/posts/military-intention/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://translusion.github.com/posts/military-intention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cenk Uygur of the Young Turks news show covered a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tkBRVRBhSso&#34;&gt;debate&lt;/a&gt; between Sam Harris and Noam Chomsky which I found interesting. I will not repeat the whole debate here but instead add my own thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally I am somewhere between Sam Harris and Noam Chomsky in opinion although I definitely used to hold Sam Harris&amp;rsquo; opinion that we in the west are completely different from the terrorists in that we do not generally kill with intention. People who die, generally die due to collateral damage. Terrorists on the other hand intentionally kill civilians intentionally to achieve their aim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that is an overly simplistic representation of the problem. Good intentions alone do not absolve you from responsibility. If you know your well intentions will invariable cause death and destruction to civilians, then you are not without guilt. If a terrorist is among a crowd of innocent civilians and you still bomb him killing civilians rather than waiting for another opportunity you are still immoral IMHO. The hypothetical perfect weapons doesn&amp;rsquo;t change this. Sure they would have just killed the terrorist with perfect weapons, however in this case they know civilians will die but still do it. The value of civilian lives has to be weighted against the importance of killing a civilian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is where I have changed. I used to believe western powers waged war in a much more honorable way only killing civilians when absolutely necessary. However it is becoming increasingly clear that there is very little consideration for saving civilian lives when the opportunity to kill a terrorist presents itself. The death of a terrorist is simply valued too high, while the value assigned to civilians seems terribly low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analogy with perfect weapons is completely flawed. Terrorism is an a strategy employed by militarily weak forces. They are incapable of hurting the military of their opponents in any meaningful way. That is why they employ terrorism instead. It is easier to hurt and injure civilians. If we consider the Basque, Catalan separatists, IRA, PLO, PKK and Jewish terrorist organizations like Irgun they have all used terrorism to attempt to force a militarily superior force to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So contrary to what Sam Harris claims, if terrorists had perfect weapons they would have hit military targets alone as well. Also conventional forces frequently employ terrorism to force terrorists or guerrilla to stop. As Cenk Uygur mentions Israel frequently terrorize the Palestinian population after terror attacks for force them to stop terrorism. Donald Trump also recently advocated killing family members of civilians. The idea is presumably to discourage potential terrorist through threats against their family. Likewise the British terrorized civilians in Ireland to kill the support of the IRA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is really hard to imagine what perfect weapons are. If perfect weapons can only kill slowly but accurately, that would still encourage both parties western or not to terrorize civilians. E.g. if perfect weapons could not kill terrorist fast enough, the west would easily start thinking like the USA in the Vietnam or Philippines or British in Ireland or South African Boer war to employ terrorist actions to intimidate the enemy into giving up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So basically I think the west does have the moral upper hand in this war against terror, but I think the upper hand is not nearly has big as we like to imagine. Indiscriminate killing of civilians can&amp;rsquo;t be excused on the ground that we primarily intended to kill terrorists. Again and again we are chose strategies which put more civilians at risk to reduce the risk for western soldiers. A morally superior military force would put their own soldiers in higher danger to safe civilians.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I don&#39;t believe in Torture</title>
      <link>http://translusion.github.com/posts/torture/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://translusion.github.com/posts/torture/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This is a rather hillarious heading, because who in their right mind believes in torture. Most people will say &amp;ldquo;I support human rights&amp;rdquo;. But then there are those who come with a big BUT. But there are of course those exceptional cases they say where an attack is imminent and we could tward the terrorists from killing thousands. This might of course also question how valuable is really human rights which only extends to those you love or deem good people, while nasty people don&amp;rsquo;t get it. It is much like free speech. If you argue free speech should only be allowed to those who don&amp;rsquo;t say nasty things, then it isn&amp;rsquo;t free speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway the two common assumptions proponents of torture of terrorists indulge in is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That you are always able to tell whether the terrorist is telling the truth or not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That you know that you got the right guy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a realistic scenario you don&amp;rsquo;t know who knows what. Say you got 10 terror suspects and one of them knows where the next attack is going to be. You don&amp;rsquo;t know who knows however and when you ask each of them, they all refuse to tell you. So you decide to torture every one of them to force them to talk. Now everyone of them wants to get away from the pain so they say whatever they think you want to hear. 9 of them has to invent something, because there is only 1 who actually knows. Problem is that now you have 10 different answers to your question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the problem is that even if we assumed torture made people tell the truth if they know it, it wont help because the whole torture approach is producing so many false answers that you can&amp;rsquo;t tell when you got the right answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is silly assumption that the authorities can really know for sure whether they got the right person or not. As the Senate Committee&amp;rsquo;s Report on CIA&amp;rsquo;s use of torture details, one often apperhended innocents. In fact 20% of those detained did not even meet CIA&amp;rsquo;s own criteria for being detained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great example of this is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guildford_Four_and_Maguire_Seven#Guildford_Four&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Guildford Four and Maguire Seven&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; who were convicted of the Guildford pub bombings of 5 October 1974. This later formed the basis of the famous movie &amp;ldquo;In the name of my father&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Convictions based on the use of torture. They were not released until 1991, when it was uncovered how the police had manipulated evidence and tortured the suspects into confessions. No doubt the police thought they had the right guys. When it started becoming clear they were wrong they covered up. That is third problem with torture. If one ever makes a mistake in torture, authorities will attempt to cover up the truth because the truth will be too much of an embarrasment. Just like the catholic chrurch has covered up their abuses because what could be more embarrassing that the guardians of moral displaying imoral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusion:8e3e3848c75d40eaae37bf7322309ce4&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in short I believe torture is wrong because when we torture we create a lot of false positives which hides the actual truth. Secondly because the principle of innocence exists not to be nice to bad guys but because it is very hard to know whether you got the right guy. That is why we have courts, to determine innocence. It stands to reasons that the graver the accusation the stronger the legal protection should be as the moral cost of wrongefully convicting someone of mass murder or terrorism is very high. Sadly many seem to conclude opposite. The more terrible the accusation you are subject to the less legal protection you deserve. With this form of logic, going over the speed limit on the highway should give someone the strongest legal defence.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>